Guide to the Lady Mary Hamilton Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lady Mary Hamilton papers
1758-1863
OSB MSS 75
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.97
(3 boxes)
Series I, Letterbook of Lady Mary Hamilton, contains correspondence by and to the author Lady Mary Hamilton, principally with her daughter Betsey Walker Thiébault and her son-in-law Paul Thiébault; her siblings, including Anne Leslie Carnegie, Countess of Northesk, and Alexander Leslie; and with George Robinson Hamilton and Sir Herbert Croft. Series II, Family Papers, contains a detailed biographical memoir of Lady Mary by her grandson, Baron Adolphe Thiébault.
Hamilton, Mary, Lady, 1739-1816
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the James Marshall Osborn Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is also available on microfilm.
LADY MARY HAMILTON, 1739-1816
Lady Mary Hamilton was born Lady Mary Leslie, youngest daughter of Alexander Leslie, 5th Earl of Leven and Melville, and Lady Elizabeth Monypenny Leslie. She married Dr. James Walker of Innerdovat, physician to the prison hospital in Edinburgh, on January 5, 1762. It was said to have been a "romantic" match, but she and Walker came to lead very separate lives.
According to her grandson, Lady Mary bore ten children, several of whom died in infancy. In 1782 she met and became involved with George Robinson Hamilton, a cousin of the Duke of Hamilton, and removed to France with him and two of her daughters, Betsey and Isabella. After the French Revolution, Betsey married Paul Thiébault, who became General Thiébault, while Isabella married Etienne de Jouy.
Lady Mary Hamilton, as she styled herself, was best known for her novel Munster Village (1778), a utopian work depicting a community of women pursuing higher education, but she also published Letters from the Duchess de Crony (1777); The Life of Mrs. Justman (1782); and The Duc de Popoli (1810).
George Robinson Hamilton died in October, 1797. Some time after his death Lady Mary moved to Amiens, where Sir Herbert Croft became a member of her household. She died there early in 1816, shortly before Croft himself.
Scope and Contents
The Lady Mary Hamilton Papers consist of letters and family papers documenting aspects of the life of Lady Mary Hamilton. The papers span the dates 1758-1863, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1790s, and are organized into two series: I. Letterbook of Lady Mary Hamilton; and II. Family Papers.
Series I, Letterbook of Lady Mary Hamilton, is housed in Box 1, folders 1-128 and consists of letters and a few other papers which were gathered and bound by her grandson, Baron Adolphe Thiébault. The letters have been disbound but have been kept in the order in which Thiébault arranged them, which is roughly chronological.
The first 44 folders in the series contain letters from Hamilton's relatives and social acquaintances in Scotland and England. Correspondents include her siblings, Alexander Leslie and Anne Leslie Carnegie, Countess of Northesk; Sir Henry Erskine; Henry Dundas; and Lord Balgonie. Topics include Lady Mary's financial needs; plans for the education and careers of her various children, particularly her sons; advice on settling "quietly in the country;" and social news. Folder 9 contains a letter from the Countess of Northesk describing the secret marriage and subsequent disinheritance of her eldest son Lord Rosehill; folder 34 a letter from Henry Dundas declining to assist her in her "case" beyond "barely a mention" of it to Lord North; and folder 37 contains a copy of a poem by Sir Henry Erskine.
There are over forty letters in the collection from Lady Mary to her daughter Betsey Walker Thiébault, addressed to "my dear daughter" or to "Kanker" (a nickname derived from her astrological sign). The letters discuss Lady Mary's and George Hamilton's opposition to, and eventual approval of, Betsey's impending marriage to Thiébault, then a soldier in the Revolutionary Army, as well as her continuing difficulties with her in-laws over dowry and settlement agreements. They also contain news of her siblings and her extended family in Scotland; refer obliquely to political events and developments, particularly Lady Mary's fears of persecution as a foreign national during the Revolutionary period; and reveal Lady Mary's own complex financial problems, which increased after the death of Hamilton in October, 1797.
Other letters include several by Sir Herbert Croft; notes concerning the confiscation of "cheveaux de luxe" by the local Revolutionary committees; six letters from George Robinson Hamilton to various recipients; and notes from Lady Mary to her grandchildren. Folder 95 contains a passport issued to Hamilton by Napoleon's police.
Series II, Family Papers, is housed in Box 2, folders 129-132 and contains extensive genealogical notes and biographical information compiled by Lady Mary Hamilton's grandson, Baron Adolphe Thiébault. The "histoire de ma famille maternelle" includes Thiébault's impressions of his grandmother and commentary on topics as diverse as the probable paternity of several of her children during her marriage to Walker; analysis of her "romantique" temperment and love of her children; and his view of the character of Sir Herbert Croft.
Prenuptial agreements; English fiction -- 18th century; Families -- England -- Domestic relations; Novelists, English -- 18th century; Women authors, English -- 18th century; Women authors; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799; France -- Social conditions -- 18th century; Women authors; Croft, Herbert, Sir, 1751-1816; Erskine, Henry, Sir, d. 1765; Hamilton, George Robinson; Hamilton, Mary, Lady, 1739-1816; Jouy, Étienne de, 1764-1846; Northesk, Anne Leslie Carnegie, Countess of.; Northesk, William Carnegie, Earl of, 1758-1831; Thiébault, Adolphe, baron; Thiébault, Paul Charles François Adrien Henri Dieudonné, baron, 1769-1846
- Letterbook of Lady Mary Hamilton, 1758-1859; Series I; 0.41; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Letterbook of Lady Mary Hamilton, is arranged in its original binding order.
  - Fragments found in the gutter of the volume when disbound in 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wrapper: "Lettres et papiers de Lady Mary Walker, nee Lester (1756 a 1816)", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Table of contents, 1859 Jul 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Table of contents of the letterbook written by Baron Thiébault, grandson of Lady Mary Hamilton. In French.
  - ALS from Elizabeth Monypenny Leslie, Countess of Leven; Edinburgh, 1781 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Docket: "My mother the Countess Dowager of Leven her last letter dated December 1781" With: lock of the Countess of Leven's hair
  - ALS from James Walker [of Kinnaird to his daughter Isabella], 1788 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Blank sheet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Promissory note from Daniel MacKercher to James Walker for L 150, 1771 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ALS from David Leslie, Earl of Leven; Melvill, n.y. Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ALS from Anne Leslie Carnegie, Countess of Northesk; Edinburgh, 1767 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Docket: "Letter Lady Northesk to Lady Mary with copy of Letter from Ld Rosehill to Lord Northesk and Lady Northesks Answer" March 14 No. 5" (these letters not present)
  - ALS from Anne Leslie Carnegie, Countess of Northesk, n.y. Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    "My Sister the Countess of Northesk her last Letter to me"
  - AN (in the third person) from David Carnegie, Earl of Northesk, 1785 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ALS from [Alexander Leslie of Beechwood]; Money Moon, County of Derry, 1763 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Signed "AL"
  - Slip of paper, 1763 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Bank, 1763 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Callidan, 1763 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Blank sheet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Edinburgh, 1783 Apr 9 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Blank sheet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ALS to David Walker from Alexander Leslie; Edinburgh, 1791 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Edinburgh, 1791 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Edinburgh, 1791 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Edinburgh, 1792 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ALS from Alexander Leslie; Edinburgh, 1792 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ALS from [Alexander Leslie]; Edinburgh, 1792 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - AL (incomplete) from unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - AL from unidentified, 1783 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Blank sheet cut in middle, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - ALS from unidentified; Brewer Street, 1784 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - AL (in the third person) from General Alexander Melville to General Thiébault; London, Brewer Street, 1802 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - ALS from Henry Frederick, Duke of Cumberland; Cumberland House, 1777 or 1778 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    "Letter from the late Duke of Cumberland" Signed "Henry"
  - ALS from Lord Balgonie; Balgonie Castle, 1802 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Addressed to "my dear Aunt;" announces the death of the Earl of Leven and Melville
  - ALS from Elizabeth Crompton Hume-Campbell, Countess of Marchmont; Hemel Hempstead, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Signed "E Marchmont"
  - ALS from Elizabeth Crompton Hume-Campbell, Countess of Marchmont, 1778 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - ALS from Henry Dundas (later Viscount Melville); Saville Row, 1779 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Docket: "Mr. Dundass 1779"
  - ALS from William Wildman Barrington, Viscount Barrington; Paultons in Hampshire, 1781 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - ALS from Sir Henry Erskine; Pall-Mall, 1758 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Docket: "Sir Harry Erskines Letter and my answer 1757"
  - "The Goose:" AMS, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    "Sir Harry Erskines Verse"
  - AL (in the third person) from MH to Sir Henry Erskine; Leven Lodge, 1759 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Opens: "Lady Mary Leslie is concerned..."
  - AL (in the third person) from Sir Henry Erskine; Pall-Mall, 1759 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - ALS to Miss Glen, 1767 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Signed: "M. Walker"
  - AL (incomplete) from unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - AL draft, incomplete and corrected, from unidentified (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - ALS from MH to [Alexander Melville?], 1784 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "Dialogues:" AMS concerning conversation between MH and Mr. Morgan, 1787 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - ALS from MH to [Etienne de] Jouy; Lille, 1793 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], [1793?] Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, [1793?] Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], [1793?] Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1793 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], [1793?] Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1793 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1793 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - ALS from M. Hamilton to "Citoyen Thiébault" [Paul Thiébault]; Lille, 1793 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - ALS from MH to "My dear daughter;" Lille, 1793 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Addressed: "Au Citoyen Thiébault"
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1794 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1794 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1794 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1794 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1794 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1794 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1794 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1795 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Equeberg?, 1795 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Equeberg?, 1795 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1795 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - ALS from MH to Paul [Thiébault]; Lille, 1797 23 Feb (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Congratulations on the birth of his son. In French.
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault; Lille, [1797]
    Written on printed "Epitaph" for "George Robinson Hamilton, Esq.... Obit 29th October 1797."
  - AMS concerning legal difficulties in the settlement of Hamilton's estate, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault; Lille, 1798 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    In French.
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault; Lille, 1801 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    In French. With: ALS from MH to Betsey Walker, n.d., attached to accounting note dated 1802 Apr 26.
  - ALS from MH to Adolphe Thiébault, 1802 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; 9 Buckingham Street, Strand, London, 1801 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; 6 Adam Street, Adelphi, [London], 1801 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Lille, 1802 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault; Lille, 1802 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    In French. With: fragment of AL to Betsey Walker, 1802 Jun 28
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault; Lille, 1802 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault; Lille, 1802 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Empty folder (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault, 1802 Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - ALS from MH to Paul Thiébault, 1802 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    In French. With: accounts concerning the settlement of Hamilton's estate, n.d.
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1804 Feb 24 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    With: "Paper of consequence respecting the debts and payments made to the créanciers de feu M. Hamilton," n.d.
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1804 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1804 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1804 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1804 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1804 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1803 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - ALS from MH to Adolphe [Thiébault]; Amiens, 1806 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - ALS from MH to Sir Herbert Croft, 1806 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    Addressed: "A Monsieur Monsieur Le Chevalier Croft No. 4 Rue des Augustins a Amiens"
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Amiens, 1806 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; Amiens, 1806 Jul 21 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - ALS (incomplete) from MH, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1810 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    "6 January, I open the letter to tell you it was neglected to be put in the post."
  - ALS from MH to Adolphe Thiébault; Amiens, 1806 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - ALS from MH to Adolphe Thiébault, 1810 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Passport issued to MH by the Police Générale for travel between Amiens and Lille, 1808 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    Printed form, filled out, stamped and signed
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1810 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1810 Sept 23 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - ALS from MH to Adolphe, Laure and [Betsey Walker], 1812 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker]; London, 1814 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - AL (incomplete) from MH to [Betsey Walker]; London, 1814 Nov (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - ALS from MH to "Bell" [Isabella Walker Jouy]; Jamaica, 1815 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1815 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    With: ALS to "David"
  - Engraved calling card: "Lady Mary Hamilton", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - ALS from MH to [Betsey Walker], 1816 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - ALS from MH to "Emma;" Londres?, 1816 "fin de" (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - ALS from George Robinson Hamilton to MH; Bristol, 1791 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - ALS from George Robinson Hamilton to [Etienne de] Jouy; Lille, 1793 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - ALS from MH to Paul [Thiébault], 1793 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - ALS from George Robinson Hamilton to Paul [Thiébault]; Lille, 1793 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - ALS from George Robinson Hamilton to "Monsieur;" Lille, 1793 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - ALS from George Robinson Hamilton to "mon cher ami;" Lille, 1793 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - ALS from DeGras? concerning the confiscation of horses by order of "citoyen Griois, commisaire nationale", 1795 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 111)
    In French
  - ALS from Dubais concerning the confiscation of "cheveaux de luxe", 1795 Jun 11 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - "Soliloquy:" AMS by unidentified, n.y. Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - AL (in the third person) from Sir Herbert Croft to David Walker, copy of letter from Croft to his brother Richard, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - ALS from Sir Herbert Croft to Madame Thiébault [Betsey Walker]; Amiens, n.y. Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - AL incomplete from unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - ALS from Sir Herbert Croft to Madame Thiébault, 1816 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - ALS from Sir Herbert Croft to "Dear Madam", n.y. Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - ALS from Sir Herbert Croft to Madame Thiébault; Amiens, 1807 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - ALS from Sir Herbert Croft to Madame Thiébault, 1807 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - "Sir Herbert Croft, Bart. to Mademoiselle de Jouy...:" AMS of poem, 1810 Jul (Box 1, Folder 121)
    First line: "Dear Emma! This old ugly Latin,..." With: ALS from Croft to "Dear Madam," 1812 Mar 17
  - AL (incomplete), unidentified, n.y. Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Letter fragment with notes, by MH and Sir Herbert Croft (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - ALS from Sir Herbert Croft to "Mon cher hermite", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - AL to Lord Leven, 1803 Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Genealogical notes on cousins-german, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - List of people, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - ALS to [MH] from "De Matigny", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 128)
- Family Papers, 1863; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series II, Family Papers, is arranged alphabetically by title and type of material.
  - "Complément à l'histoire de ma famille maternelle....ou, Histoire de Lady Mary Walker et de ses enfants", 1863 Mar 30 (Box 2, Folder 129-30)
    Autograph manuscript signed of family history by Baron Adolphe Thiébault, grandson of Lady Mary Walker Hamilton
  - Manuscript notes for family history, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Original binding of letterbook (Box 2, Folder 132)
- Oversize, 1.34; (1 box)
  - Obit notice for George Robinson Hamilton, 1797 Oct 29 (Box 3, Folder 133)